Finding Aid for Dept. of English Language and Literature (University of Michigan) Publications 1930-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dept. of English Language and Literature (University of Michigan) Publications 1930-2002, 1971-2002
University of Michigan. Dept. of English Language and Literature.
1.3 linear foot
Publications produced the University of Michigan Department of English Language and Literature, its sub-units and student organizations, including newsletters, anthologies, reports, histories, flyers and posters.
0363, Bimu, C26, 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Publications are received at regular intervals from the Department of English Language and Literature (Donor No. 1802 ).
The publications group is open without restriction.
For background of this unit, please consult the history found in the Department of English Language and Literature Records finding aid.
The Department of English Language and Literature Publications, (1.3 linear feet) include brochures, flyers, newsletters, and posters as well as student publications and faculty publications, dating from the years 1942 to 2001. There are four series: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications, Student Publications and Topical Publications.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Dept. of English Language and Literature.; University of Michigan. Avery Hopwood and Jule Hopwood Prizes.; Blue ox review.; Xylem.; Avery Hopwood and Jule Hopwood awards in creative writing, reports on the contests and statement of rules.
Genre/Form:
Newsletters.; Student publications.; Bibliographies.; Reports.; Brochures.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series contains printed material published specifically by the Department of English Language and Literature. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication.
  The majority of the Unit Publications series is comprised of an incomplete run of department newsletters. These include the English Department Newsletter published from 1942 to 1945 describing some of the activities of war-time students and alumni. The Newsletter was issued from 1971 to 1975 though other issues may be available elsewhere. The Bentley Library holds copies of the department newsletter Crossroads for the period from 1992 to 1997.
  - Bibliographies
    - Faculty Publications, 1967-1972 (supplement to Report on the Department), undated (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - English, 1954-1993, undated (Box 1)
    - Graduate Studies in English Language and Literature, 1972-1992, undated (Box 1)
    - Words in the Mourning Time: A Celebration of Robert Hayden's Poetry, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Flyers
    - E-Mail (print outs) 1997 (Box 1)
    - A Four-Year Program of Graduate Study Leading to the Doctor of Philosophy Degree, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1995, undated (Box 1)
  - Newsletters
    - Crossroads, vol. 1-6, 1992-1997 (Box 1)
    - The Department of English Language and Literature Newsletter, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Dept. of English newsletter 1997-2000 (Box 1)
    - English at Michigan, 1993 (Box 1)
    - English Department Newsletter, 1942-1945, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - News and notes 1993-1999 (Box 1)
    - Newsletter, 1971-1975 (Box 1)
  - Plays
    - Play Production programs (Box 1)
  - Posters
    - Miscellaneous undated (Box 1)
    - Victorian Semester, Winter 1984 (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - Report on the Department of English, 1973 (Box 1)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  The Sub-Unit Publications series contains publications from subordinate offices, departments, programs and organizations within the Department of English Language and Literature. These publications are arranged alphabetically by the creating sub-unit.
  Of most interest in the Sub-Unit Publications series are the materials relating to the Avery Hopwood and Jule Hopwood Awards in Creative Writing. These include Reports on the Contests and Statements of Rules, which contain the names of the winners for each year and range from 1930 to 2001. The Bentley Historical Library holds a nearly complete run of this publication. The Hopwood Newsletter, published from 1942 to the present, chronicles the publications and activities of former Hopwood Award winners. There are also two anthologies and several reprints of the Hopwood Lectures. The Hopwood Lecture is given during the awards ceremony in April. A prominent writer is invited to speak on a subject which he/she feels is important to young writers. Additional material regarding the Hopwood Awards can be found in the Hopwood Awards collection at the Department of Rare Books and Special Collections, Harlan Hatcher Graduate Library, University of Michigan.
  - Avery Hopwood and Jule Hopwood Awards in Creative Writing
    - Flyers 1984-1986, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Histories
      - undated (Box 1)
      - A remarkable legacy: Hopwood winners from Arthur Miller to Elizabeth Kostova, 2006 (Box 1)
    - Lectures
      - 1988-1993, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Speaking of Writing: Selected Hopwood Lectures, edited by Nicholas Delbanco, 1990 (Box 1)
      - The Writer's Craft: Hopwood Lectures, 1965-1981 edited by Robert A. Martin, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Newsletters
      - The Hopwood Newsletter 1942-ongoing, 9 folders (Box 1)
    - Posters 1988-1992 (Box 1)
    - Reports
      - Reports of the Contests and Statements of Rules
        - 1930-1990, 10 folders (Box 1)
      - Reports of the Contests and Statements of Rules (Box 2)
        - 1991-2003 (Box 2)
  - Committee on Scholarly and Creative Activities
    - Newsletters
      - The COSCA Reporter, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - The Composition Program
    - Report, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Graduate Program
    - Regulations
      - Requirements, Regulations and Programs for Graduate Students in English Language and Literature, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - Doctor of Arts in English Program Conference
      - Programs and Newsletters 1980 (Box 2)
    - Master of Fine Arts in Creative Writing
      - MFA newsletter 1995-1997 (Box 2)
      - Poster 1990/91 (Box 2)
    - Poster Graduate Programs in English, undated (Box 2)
  - Honors Colloquium
    - Anthologies
      - Writes of Passage, 1987 (Box 2)
  - The Marjorie Rapaport Award in Poetry
    - Flyers undated (Box 2)
  - Michigan Writers' Conference
    - Brochures 1959-1965 (Box 2)
- Student Publications
  The Student Publications series contains publications published by student groups within the Department of English Language and Literature.
  The Student Publications series consists of both graduate and undergraduate publications. There are anthologies from the Creative Writing Program in 1976. The Undergraduate English Association published several volumes of The Barbaric Yawp for the period from 1984 to 1994. There are also two volumes of Xylem, the successor to The Barbaric Yawp, dating from 1995 to 1996. Also included in this series is the anthology The Blue Ox Review dating from 1984 to 1985.
  - Creative Writing Program
    - Anthologies
      - Figures, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Introductory Composition Program
    - Newsletters
      - The GSTA Newsletter, 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - Undergraduate English Association
    - Anthologies
      - Barbaric Yawp, 1984-1994, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Xylem, 1995-1996 2004/2005 [Supersedes The Barbaric Yawp] (Box 2)
    - Newsletters
      - Fortnight, 2001 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Student Publications
    - Anthologies
      - The Blue Ox Review, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters
      - DA News, 1974 (Box 2)
      - The Fresh Press, 1979, undated (Box 2)
      - TA Newsletter, 1975, undated (Box 2)
- Topical Publications
  - Summer Session
    - Programs
      - Conference of English Teachers, 1952-1961, 1968 (Box 2)